Finding Aid for the Leo Smit Papers, 1939-2000
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Leo Smit Papers, 1939-2000
Mus. Arc. 6.2
Smit, Leo, 1921-1999
4 boxes (49 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Leo Smit Papers comprise works lists compiled by Leo Smit, articles written by Smit, personal correspondence (chiefly photocopies of letters from Aaron Copland), programs, reviews, and lecture materials.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection was given to the Music Library in 1998 by Leo Smit. Subsequent additions were donated by executor of Leo Smit's estate, Nils Vigeland, or provided by the staff of the Music Library.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Leo Smit was born to Russian immigrants on January 12, 1921, in Philadelphia. He received his earliest musical training from his father, Kolman Smit, beginning at age five. Kolman Smit was a professional violinist who performed in the Philadelphia Orchestra (1926-1931) under Leopold Stokowski, the Cincinnati Symphony under Fritz Reiner, and the NBC Symphony under Arturo Toscanini.
After private piano studies with Martha Lantner, Joseph Wissof, and Bert Shefter, Smit traveled to Moscow with his mother in 1929 to study piano for three months with Dmitri Kabalevsky on scholarship at the Moscow Conservatory. Upon his return to Philadelphia, Smit received a scholarship in 1930 to study piano at Curtis Institute of Music with noted piano pedagogue Isabelle Vengerova. He continued his studies on scholarship in New York, studying piano with José Iturbi (1933-35) and composition with Nicolas Nabokov (1935). It was under Nabokov's tutelage that Smit produced his first original composition in 1935, Zvay, a song setting of a Yiddish poem by Mani Loeb for soprano and piano.
Smit began his professional career as a pianist while still in his teens. His first professional engagement was as rehearsal pianist for George Balanchine's American Ballet Company in 1936-37. A year after beginning in this position, Smit met Igor Stravinsky during rehearsals of the composer's ballet, Jeu de Cartes. Smit gave his debut recital as a solo pianist at Carnegie Hall in February 1939. His successful debut was followed by a concert tour of the United States in 1940.
Leo Smit's career as composer, pianist, conductor, and educator spanned seven decades of musical life in the United States. He established close working relationships, and/or friendships, with many of the most prominent musicians of the 20th century, including Igor Stravinsky, Béla Bartók, Aaron Copland, Leonard Bernstein, Harold Shapero, William Schuman, Alex Haieff, Leopold Stokowski, and Lukas Foss. As a performer, Smit was an enthusiastic and persuasive advocate and interpreter of the music of his time, especially the solo piano music of Aaron Copland. His compositional output totals more than one hundred works, including two operas, three symphonies, more than ninety songs, two ballets, and numerous chamber and piano works.
Smit was also a talented photographer. In addition to the many photographs he took of noted musicians, Smit also used his skill as a photographer to capture images from his travels. Many of his travel pictures reflect his reverence for nature. As part of his innovative approach to programming, Smit would often include displays of his photography in his theme-based concerts.
During his career Leo Smit earned several awards and honors, including Fulbright (piano) and Guggenheim (composition) Fellowships in 1950, a fellowship at the American Academy in Rome for 1950-51, the Boston Symphony Merit Award in 1953 for his Symphony No. 1 (premiered October 16, 1953 by the Boston Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Charles Munch), the New York Critics Circle Award in 1957 (also for his Symphony No. 1), his selection as an artist for a State Department concert tour of Latin America in 1967-68, and the Buffalo Evening News Man of the Year award in 1969. As an educator, Smit held positions at Sarah Lawrence College (1947-49), UCLA (1957-63), and the State University of New York at Buffalo (1962-84).
Leo Smit died December 12, 1999 in Scripps Hospital, Encinitas, California.
Scope and Content Note
This collection of papers was received from Leo Smit in 1998 before he moved from Buffalo, N.Y. to California. It has been supplemented with more materials by Music Library staff and Nils Vigeland, executor of the Smit estate. Much of the supplementary material consists of photocopied materials. The small number of personal documents include a curriculum vitae dating from 1980 and a works list compiled by Smit in 1995. Also included are notification of and receipt for an inheritance from the estate of Aaron Copland. The 21 writings by Leo Smit in the collection include published articles about Aaron Copland, Johann Sebastian Bach, and Cole Porter. Also included are unpublished writings, program notes and libretti for his own works.
The correspondence in the collection consists chiefly (more than 90%) of photocopies of letters from Aaron Copland to Leo Smit. They reveal the affection Copland held for Smit and contain details of their many musical collaborations.
Clippings and reviews (27), programs (21), and promotional material (4) provide some details about Leo Smit's career. Four of Smit's lecture-recitals on American piano music, the music of Franz Liszt, American songs, and the life and music of Peter Ilyich Tchaikovsky are documented by compilations of music used for the programs.
The principal collection of Leo Smit materials is held by New York Public Library.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series:
I. Personal documents
II. Writings by Leo Smit
III. Correspondence
IV. Clippings and reviews
V. Programs
VI. Promotion and publicity
VII. Lecture materials
VIII.
Container List
- Personal documents, circa 1940-1995, I; Folders 1-6
  In order as received.
  Curriculum vitae, works lists, and notification of inheritance from estate of Aaron Copland
  - Curriculum vitae, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Works list, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Works remaining with ASCAP, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Works coming to BMI, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aaron Copland legacy notification and receipt, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Title page and page 1 of Aaron Copland's Four Piano Blues with dedication to Smit on p. 1 caption, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings by Leo Smit, circa 1960-1999, II.; Folders 7-27
  Arranged alphabetically by title of text.
  21 published and unpublished writings, program notes, and libretti, arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Aaron Copland, 1900-1990, Published in: Keyboard, March 1991: 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alchemy of Love: notes (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cantata for a Roman Lady: libretto on words by Catullus (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Classic Cole Porter, Published in: Saturday Review Dec. 25, 1971: 48-49, 57 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - For Aaron, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - For Aaron, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - In Woods: notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interview with Vivian Perlis about Aaron Copland, Printed in Copland: Since 1943, (1989) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Introduction to Liszt in Italy (lecture) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Johann Sebastian Bach: Fox or Hedgehog: a tribute on his 300th birthday, Published in: Keyboard Classics, January 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Magic Water: synopsis (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - On artistic obsession, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pianista: a concert journal, Clavier July-August, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pianista Noteamericano: a concert and travel journal, 1969? (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Remarks addressed to graduating music students at SUNY/Buffalo, New York, May 15, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Remembering Aaron Copland, 1988 (written after Copland's death in 1990) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sir Fred Hoyle: introduction (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Symphony of Dances and Songs: notes by the composer (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - To Aaron Copland (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Translation of two songs from Stravinsky's Four Russian Songs (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Trishky: (short story?) (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1940-1997, III.; Folders 28-34
  Arranged chronologically, with undated material last.
  94 letters, chiefly photocopies of letters from Aaron Copland to Leo Smit. Filed chronologically
  - 1940-1949, 14 letters on 11 leaves (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1950-1959, 26 letters on 28 leaves (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1960-1969, 17 letters on 18 leaves (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1970-1979, 25 letters on 25 leaves (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1980-1989, 8 letters on 8 leaves (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1995-1997, 2 letters on 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Undated, 2 letters on 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Clippings and reviews, 1962-2000, IV.; Folders 35-38
  Arranged chronologically
  27 photocopies and original documents, including 3 obituaries.
  - 1962-1967, 10 clippings (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1976-1979, 7 clippings (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1981-1984, 3 clippings (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1994-2000, 7 clippings, including 3 obituaries (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Programs, 1939-2000, V.; Folders 39-42
  21 photocopies and originals
  - 1939-1958, 3 programs (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 1962-1978, 7 programs (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1980-1983, 7 programs (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1994-2000, 4 programs (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Promotion and publicity, 1969-1986, VI.; Folder 43
  4 pieces
  - 1969-1986, 4 pieces (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Lecture materials, 1960-1996, VII.; Folders 44-47
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  Materials, chiefly photocopies of music, used for lecture-concerts by Leo Smit
  - Crazy Quilt of American Piano Music (no lecture texts, only music) (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Music:
    Kern, Jerome: Siren's song (p. 1 only)
    Shapero, Harold. Mister La Sol
    Gottschalk, Louis. Ossian, op. 4
    Farwell, Arthur. Polytonal study, op. 109, no. 20
    Fine, Irving. Red Queen's Gavotte
    Cage, John. Suite for Toy Piano
    MacDowell, Edward. In Deep Woods, op. 62
    Copland, Aaron. Three Moods
    Copland, Aaron. Two Piano Pieces
    Burge, David. Incomplete work from Contemporary Keyboard
    Schuman, William. Three Piano Moods
    Cage, John: Dream
    Programs:
    September 9, 1995. Brooks-Rogers Recital Hall, Williams College, Williamstown, MA (includes photocopy proof)
    September 17, 1995. Gerald G. Wilmot Hall of Music, Nazareth College, Rochester, NY (includes texts to Emily Dickinson songs)
    April 19, 1996. Karl Geiringer Hall, University of California, Santa Barbara
  - Liszt in Italy (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Text:
    Introduction to Liszt in Italy (Typescript (2 leaves))
    Music: (2 photocopied sets of the following works)
    Liszt, Franz: Angelus!
    Liszt, Franz: Carillon
    Liszt, Franz: Les Funerailles
    Liszt, Franz: Consolation No. 3
    Liszt, Franz: Liebesträume: Notturno no. II
    Liszt, Franz: Il Pensieroso
    Liszt, Franz: Canzonetta del Salvator Rosa
    Liszt, Franz: Miserer
    Liszt, Franz: Les Jeus d'Eaux à la Villa d'Este
    Wagner, Richard: Isolden's Liebestod
    Liszt, Franz: Kleine Stücke
    Liszt, Franz: Sursum Corda
    Additional music:
    Bach, Johann Sebastian: Cantata no. 161. Der Lieb zwar in der Erden (Chorale)
    Liszt, Franz: La Notte. With typescript letter from Paul Pascal, University of Washington, July 11, 1997, regarding literary allusions in the Liszt work
    Liszt, Franz: Harmonies poetiques. Invocation
    Liszt, Franz: Abschied
    Liszt, Franz: Unstern
    Liszt, Franz: En rêve
    Liszt, Franz: Nuages gris
    Liszt, Franz: Angelus
    Liszt, Franz: Consolations
    Liszt, Franz: Five Hungarian Folksongs
    Liszt, Franz: Glockenspiel (Carillon)
    Schumann, Robert: Liebeslied
    June 11, 1986. Gartner Auditorium, Cleveland Museum of Art, Cleveland, Ohio
    May 31, 1995. Gartner Auditorium, Cleveland Museum of Art, Cleveland, Ohio. With typescript letter (1 leaf) from Lita Grier to Leo Smit
  - Songs (no lecture title provided) (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Porter, Cole: Art
    Porter, Cole: I am in love
    Porter, Cole: Cherry pies ought to be you
    Porter, Cole: Trust your destiny to a star
    Porter, Cole: No lover
    Porter, Cole: Nobody's chasing me
    Porter, Cole: Red, hot and blue
    Porter, Cole: A little skipper from heaven above
    Porter, Cole: Where oh where
    Porter, Cole: Fresh as a daisy
    Porter, Cole: Most gentlemen don't like love
    Porter, Cole: Blow, Gabriel, blow
    Porter, Cole: Give me the land
    Raksin, David: Laura
    Ives, Charles: Songs my mother taught me
    Ives, Charles: The circus band
    Ives, Charles: Walking
    Ives, Charles: The greatest man. (2 copies)
    Blitzstein, Marc: Jimmie's got a goil
    Rorem, Ned: Snake
    Citkowitz, Israel: Gentle lady
    Carter, Elliott: The line-gang
    Thomson, Virgil: Susie Asado
    Fine, Irving: Polaroli
    Kubik, Gail: The Lamb
    Gershwin, George: I can't be bothered now
    Gershwin, George: How long has this been going on?
    Bernstein, Leonard: Some other time
    Bernstein, Leonard: My house
    Bernstein, Leonard: One hundred easy ways
    Copland, Aaron (arr.): Simple gifts
  - Tchaikovsky - Self Portrait (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Tchaikovsky diary entries and letters
    circa 39 works by Tchaikovsky, mostly songs
- Books bearing inscriptions to Leo Smit, 1960-1998, VIII.; Folders 48-49
  Arranged alphabetically by author
  Published books signed by their authors.
  - Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990 Copland on music Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1960, 280 pages; 22 cm (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Bears inscription from Copland to Leo Smit.
  - Solomon, Maynard Beethoven: Second, revised edition New York, New York: Schirmer Books, 1998, xxii, 554 pages; 25 cm (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Bears inscription from Solomon to Leo Smit.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990
Subjects
Composers--New York (State)--Buffalo; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990--Correspondence
Genres
Correspondence; Programs; Clippings
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Leo Smit Score Collection, circa 1940-1998
Mus. Arc. 6.1
The collection consists of 104 scores by Leo Smit, principally in copies of holographs. There are also another 43 items arranged or transcribed by Smit, inscribed to or by Smit, scores marked for performance by Smit, and miscellaneous scores.
Leo Smit Photograph Collection, circa 1926-1999
Mus. Arc. 6.3
A collection of photographs of and by Leo Smit, with digital images online.
Remembering Leo Smit (1921-1999)
An online exhibit commemorating the life and career of Leo Smit. It contains many images of Smit as well as photographs taken by him. A list of Smit's compositions, compiled by the composer, is also included.